Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Katherine and today we're
going to be talking about a very fun game.
That's right, today we're going bowling, a
very popular sport amongst many people and
so we're going to take a
look at how you play this
sport and all the vocab
related to this great game.
All right, so let's take a listen to
our dialogue and we'll be right back.
All right, so the first thing you
need to know about bowling
is that you should never cross
that line where the lane begins.
Why not?
Because they polish
and oil it to make the
ball slide down, if you
step there you'll slip and fall.
Okay, so I got my
bowling shoes, my ball, our
names on the score card, so
now how the heck do I play this?
You throw the ball down the lane
and try to knock down all the pins.
If you do, that is called a strike.
If you don't knock the
ball down on the first
try, then you get a
chance to get the spare.
After 10 frames, we add up the
points and see who has the most.
300 is a perfect score,
but very hard to get.
Got it.
Okay, I'm going to give it a go.
Oh no, my ball went in the gutter.
I told you, it's harder than you think.
Now let a pro show you how it's done.
All right, we're back,
so now let's take a look
at some of that vocab
on language take away.
So the first word we have today
in language take away is lane.
That's right, a bowling lane, so a lane
that is where you actually play this game.
That's right, a lane is also a word
for like a road, a small narrow road.
So in bowling, this
is the flat surface, the
floor, that's long, that
you roll the ball down.
That's right.
Okay, so that's your lane.
So as you said, you
roll the ball down the
lane and you try to knock down
the pins that are at the end of the lane.
That's right, so pins are,
they're a little bit heavy.
They're usually white
and they have, they're
wide at the bottom
and narrow at the top.
They almost look like wine bottles.
Exactly.
And the goal of the game is to knock these
down, to make them fall on the ground.
That's right.
Okay.
You are using, that's where you're throwing
the ball down the lane to knock down these
pins.
Now, if you knock all of them down on
your first try, that's called the strike.
A strike, that's right.
So that means all 10 pins
fall down on your first try.
But sometimes you
don't get a strike, you
may be knocked down
eight pins and then later
on your second try because
every person gets two tries.
On your second try, you
knock down the last two pins.
Now what's that called, Marco?
So if you knock all of them down on
your second try, that's called a spare.
Okay, strike, usually
you write it with an
X, that's on the scorecard
and a spare, which
is two tries to get all 10
pins, that's a slash spare.
And if you don't get all of the
pins in two tries, you still get points.
So if you knock down
eight pins, you get
eight or if you knock
down four pins, you get four.
That's right.
If you score on your
scorecard and now each
player usually gets 10
frames or 10 different
opportunities to
knock down all the pins.
All right, so usually
these are boxes on the
scorecard and you can
play 10 frame bowling.
We're also five frame,
but it's important to
remember that each frame gives
you the opportunity to bowl two times.
Right.
All right, so you get those two tries.
Really, it's 20 total tries
to knock down these pins.
That's right.
And now if you did
really well and on every
opportunity of each
frame, you got a strike,
that means that you
would get a perfect score.
That's right, a perfect score, that
means that you made no mistakes.
You knock down all
the pins on the first try.
And now obviously down the lane, it's not
as easy as it looks because to the sides of
your bowling lane, you have this
kind of a path that's to the bottom.
So if your ball goes in
there, you can't get it out.
That's right.
So remember like I
said earlier, a lane is also
the name of a place
where we can walk or drive.
It's like a road.
Well, we have gutters,
which are on the sides
of these roads and
also in bowling gutters.
They're lower and normally
on the streets, they're for water.
In bowling, they're the places on the right
or the left side where your ball will fall.
And if your ball falls
into the gutter or it
rolls into the gutter,
you will hit no pins.
Right.
I think that's the main thing.
If your ball goes in the gutter,
you don't hit any pins at all.
It just goes straight down
and you don't hit anything.
That's right.
So it's really sad when you bowl badly
and you get a gutter ball, we call it.
That's right.
All right.
So let's take a look
at all this vocab again.
Let's listen to our dialogue and we'll
be back in a bit with fluency builder.
All right.
So the first thing you need
to know about bowling is that
you should never cross that
line where the lane begins.
Why not?
Because they polish and oil
it to make the ball slide down.
If you step there, you'll slip and fall.
Okay.
So I got my bowling shoes, my
ball, our names on the score card.
So now how the heck do I play this?
Throw the ball down the lane
and try to knock down all the pins.
If you do, that is called a strike.
If you don't knock
them all down in the first
try, then you get a
chance to get the spare.
After 10 frames, we add up the
points and see who has the most.
300 is a perfect score,
but very hard to get.
Got it.
Okay.
I'm going to give it a go.
Oh, no, my ball went in the gutter.
I told you, it's harder than you think.
Now let a pro show you how it's done.
All right, so we've picked out
three different phrases for you.
Let's take a look at those
now in Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
All right.
So the first phrase
that we have today is
something that you're
going to hear a lot, although
I want to remind everyone
this is very informal.
So we heard someone say in the dialogue,
so now how the heck do I play this?
Okay.
So how the heck do I turn this computer on?
Okay, so how do I turn this computer
on means I don't know, please help me.
But how the heck means I really
don't know, I really need your help.
That's right.
I really don't understand what's going on.
I need someone's help.
Like how the heck did this happen means
I absolutely did not expect this to happen.
I'm very surprised.
That's right.
It's actually a not
very polite phrase to
use, but at the same time,
it's not terribly in polite.
It's in the middle.
But it's very informal.
All right.
So now the person
understands how to bowl,
how the game works,
and he says, okay, got it.
I'm going, I'm going to give it a go.
Okay.
I'm gonna means I'm going
to, and this is very informal.
Gonna is a way to say going to I
will, but the phrase here is give it a go.
What does that mean, Marco?
Give it a go.
So if you're going to give it a go,
it means that you're going to try.
Okay.
So I'm gonna try.
So we could say this, now that we know
how to play the game, let's give it a go.
Let's try to play because we've been talking
about it, but we haven't been doing it.
So to give it a go means
to try to do something.
Exactly.
And that's basically it.
If maybe you're watching a
game on the street and you want to
try maybe a card game, you
say, okay, I want to give it a go.
I want to give it a go.
All right.
And what about our last phrase?
The very last phrase is the
last phrase of our dialogue.
The character says, now let
a pro show you how it's done.
All right.
So how it's done this,
let me show you how it's
done, because this
person is saying, I'm a pro.
Let me show you how it's done.
It's a very interesting
way of saying something
in English, but what is the
real meaning of this phrase?
He's basically saying now,
let me show you how to do it.
Okay.
The correct way.
Right.
He's saying, you didn't do it very well,
you didn't bowl very well, you're new.
Let me show you how professional
people, right, let me give you an example.
Exactly.
Maybe you and your
friend are making a cake
and you don't really
know what you're doing.
So your friend says, move over.
Let me show you how it's done.
That means the proper
way to do it, the correct way.
So Marco, you're not doing it right.
Let me show you how it's done.
Exactly.
A very useful phrase.
It can seem a little bit confusing because
you're using the verb, they're done.
So it may seem a little bit weird, do done.
But don't worry about it.
Just take it as a phrase.
Let me show you how to do it.
Let me show you how it's done.
That's right.
So that's all we got for
fluency builder today.
Let's take another listen to our
dialogue and we'll be back in a second.
All right.
So the first thing you
need to know about
bowling is that you should never
cross that line where the lane begins.
Why not?
Because they polish an oil it
to make the ball slide down.
If you step there, you'll slip and fall.
OK.
So I got my bowling shoes, my
ball, our names on the score card.
So now how the heck do I play this?
You throw the ball down the lane
and try to knock down all the pins.
If you do, that is called a strike.
If you don't knock them all down on the
first try, then you get a chance to get the
spare. After 10 frames, we add up
the points and see who has the most.
300 is a perfect score,
but very hard to get.
Got it.
OK, I'm going to give it a go.
Oh, no, my ball went in the gutter.
I told you, it's harder than you think.
Now let a pro show you how it's done.
All right.
We're back.
So bowling is actually a very kind of
like a past time in the United States.
You get together with friends
and you just go bowling.
That's right.
I do believe it's also considered a sport.
So many people play
professionally or semi-professionally.
But for me, it's always
been a very social
game, something you
do with a group of friends.
You go out.
It's really fun.
Yeah, it's especially because when you
go bowling, many people can play, right?
Not obviously at the same
time, but you take turns.
And so while you're waiting, people are
talking and eating, so it is a very social
activity.
That's right.
So maybe a group of
people will rent a lane.
Remember we were
talking earlier about a lane
being that one kind
of strip of wood where
you roll the ball, well, a group of
friends can rent a lane or two lanes.
And the four or the
eight of you can play
together, each person playing,
you know, one frame at a time.
That's right.
And now actually, the other thing about
it is it's very funny to see people trying
to bowl or maybe with
the heavy ball or maybe
they pass the line that we said they
shouldn't pass and they slip and fall.
So I guess that's what also
makes it a little bit fun to play.
Yes, it can be a little bit
embarrassing if you're not.
I'm not very good, so
I'm a very embarrassing
bowler, but it's also
really fun because if
you go and you just, you know, have
a nice time and it's a very social game.
Well, it is.
And actually, we are
really curious to know
if you've ever been
bowling, and many people
have never been bowling
and they find it very, very fun.
So why don't you come
to our website, englishpot.
com and leave your questions
and comments there as well.
Yeah, we hope to see you there.
Until next time, guys.
Bye.